<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: titleType-osm-fields-en-us.xml,v 1.20 2013/08/12 16:40:14 ginger Exp $ --> 
<metadataFieldInfo xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns="http://www.dlsciences.org/frameworks/fields" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.dlsciences.org/frameworks/fields http://nldr.library.ucar.edu/metadata/osm/1.1/schemas/fields/titleType.xsd">
<!--HISTORY of CHANGE
2013-08-09: kmaull - Correspondence is no longer part of the controlled vocabulary. It had the definition of: Online Dictionary for Library and Information Science (OLDIS)">letters, memoranda, notes, postcards, email, and other written and addressed messages exchanged between two or more people, usually archived with the personal papers of the correspondents.
2013-08-08: Notes is no longer part of the controlled vocabulary. It had the definition of: brief explanations or descriptions that usually supplement the understanding of a work, subject or object. Notes had a best practice of: Notes: use for descriptive technical notes or summaries.

2011-09-19: Comment is no longer a part of the controlled vocab. It had the definition of: a substantive article, letter, or editorial that challenges, refutes, supports or expands upon a previously published work; use article instead.


-->

  <field name="Title - type" metaFormat="osm" metaVersion="1.1" language="en-us" path="/record/general/title/@type">
		<definition>the nature or the genre of the resource being entered</definition> 

		<terms>
<!--abstract term removed 2011-12-16; see controlled vocabulary schema for more documentation		
			<termAndDeftn vocab="Abstract" attribution="Online Dictionary for Library and Information Science (OLDIS)">a brief, objective representation of the essential content of a book, article, speech, report, dissertation, patent, standard, or other work, presenting the main points in the same order as the original but having no independent literary value</termAndDeftn>
-->
			<termAndDeftn vocab="Animation/moving image">a medium of expression consisting of a series of related images, which create the illusion of movement when viewed in rapid succession</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Archives">primary source materials from the Archives that do not fall under any other title type, such as correspondence, newsletter, or transcript</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Article">a self-contained prose composition on a fairly narrow topic or subject, written by one or more authors and published or submitted for publication in a work with a separate title that is a collection or periodical containing works of the same form</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Artifact/physical object">a natural object or an object made or modified by one or more persons (replicas excluded)</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Bibliography/index">Bibliography: a  list of resources, often with descriptive or critical notes, pertaining to a particular subject, period, author, language, form, place of publication, or some other characteristic</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Bibliography/index">Index: an alphabetically arranged list of headings treated in a work (e.g. names, places, or subjects) and with references to point the user to the location within the resource pertaining to the heading</termAndDeftn>
			
			<termAndDeftn vocab="Blog/forum/email list"  attribution="Online Dictionary for Library and Information Science (OLDIS)">Blog: a web page that provides frequent, continuing publication of web links and/or comments on a specific topic (broad or narrow in scope), often in the form of short entries arranged in an orderly fashion, usually chronological.</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Blog/forum/email list"  attribution="Online Dictionary for Library and Information Science (OLDIS)">Forum/email list: an email discussion forum that allows individuals to subscribe and automatically receive messages posted to the list by other subscribers. Participants may also post their own messages and replies for distribution to the other subscribers to the list.</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Book chapter">one of two or more major divisions of a book or other work, each complete in itself but related in theme or structure to the division preceding and/or following it</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Book review">an evaluative account of a book, usually written by a qualified person for publication in a newspaper, magazine, or journal</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Book/monograph">Book: a written work or composition that has been published and bound as a single volume</termAndDeftn>
			<termAndDeftn vocab="Book/monograph">Monograph: a relatively short book or treatise on a single subject, that is complete in one volume, detailed and scholarly but not extensive in scope, and usually written by a specialist in the field</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Collection">a group of related items that have something in common like a shared topic, intended audience, genre or institution that has sponsored their creation, or shared provenance</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Encyclopedia">a book or numbered set of books containing authoritative summary information about a variety of topics in the form of short essays, usually arranged alphabetically or classified in some manner</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Image">a single visual representation</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Interactive resource">materials designed to respond to input from a human being, usually in the form of commands, data and/or actions</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Journal/magazine/periodical">Journal: a periodical devoted to disseminating original research and commentary on current developments in a specific discipline, subdiscipline, or field of study, usually published in quarterly, bimonthly, or monthly issues, and sold by subscription</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Journal/magazine/periodical" attribution="Online Dictionary for Library and Information Science (OLDIS)">Magazine: a popular interest periodical usually containing articles on a variety of topics, written by various authors in a nonscholarly style. Most magazines are heavily illustrated, and contain advertising.</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Journal/magazine/periodical">Periodical: a serial publication with its own distinctive title, containing a mix of articles, editorial, reviews, columns, short stories, poems, or other short works written by more than one contributor, generally published at regular stated intervals of less than a year, without prior decision as to when the final issue will appear</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Manual">a book used as a reference in the operation of a task, computer program, procedure, job or other function</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Manuscript">a written and, traditionally, unpublished work or composition</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Metadata profile">a specification that defines the properties and values of a metadata format</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Newsletter">a serial publication consisting of no more than a few pages, devoted to news, announcements, and current information that is of interest primarily to a specialized group of subscribers or members of an association or organization who receive it as part of their membership or affiliation</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Poster">a visual medium created to publicize a forthcoming event or communicate scholarly or scientific work, with or without illustration</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Presentation/webcast">a broadcast, podcast, or formal representation of ideas communicated in person or via the Internet</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Report">a record of research findings, research still in progress, or other technical findings, usually bearing a report number and sometimes a grant number assigned by the funding agency</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Software">a computer program, application, or model that must be run on a computer server</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Sound">recorded auditory material that can be heard by the human ear</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Thesis/dissertation">a written document on a particular subject in which one has done original research that is for a diploma or degree</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="Transcript">the written record of words spoken in a speech, interview, broadcast, sound recording or other proceedings</termAndDeftn>
		</terms>
		 <bestPractices>
			<dos>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2010-05-31">This is an required field.</practice> 
				<practice status="current" originDate="2010-05-31">This field cannot be repeated.</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2010-05-31">Classify  resources by what is created by the author and not what is presented to a user (e.g. OpenSky has just the citation of a paper but still call it an article.).</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2010-05-31">Classify a resource as a proceedings only when the publisher/sponsor clearly indicates it as such.  All other resources should be cataloged as a different type, most likely a presentation or poster.</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2012-11-29" link1="Thesis/dissertation" style1="bold" link2="title" style2="bold">When using Thesis/dissertation, append the degree name to the title. See examples below.</practice>
			 </dos>
			 <donts>
				 <practice status="current" originDate="2010-05-31">Do not choose a type if nothing fits. Contact the OpenSky administrator.</practice> 
			 </donts>
			 <examples>
					 <practice status="current" originDate="2012-11-29" link1="Thesis/dissertation" style1="bold">Thesis/dissertation - Masters: The saline flow into the Atlantic. M.S. thesis</practice>
					 <practice status="current" originDate="2012-11-29" link1="Thesis/dissertation" style1="bold">Thesis/dissertation - PhD: The saline flow into the Atlantic. Ph.D. dissertation</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-05-31" link1="Proceedings" style1="bold" link2="ERAD 2010 Proceedings" url2="http://www.erad2010.org/Sibiu.htm">Proceedings: ERAD 2010 Proceedings</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-05-31" link1="Proceedings" style1="bold" link2="Proceedings of the Royal Society B" url2="http://rspb.royalsocietypublishing.org/">Proceedings: Proceedings of the Royal Society B</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-05-31" link1="Not a Proceedings" style1="bold" link2="Third US-Korea Joint Workshop on Storm- and Mesoscale Weather Analysis and Prediction" url2="http://www.cosmic.ucar.edu/2002Conference/abstractsFeb02.html">Not a Proceedings: Third US-Korea Joint Workshop on Storm- and Mesoscale Weather Analysis and Prediction.</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-05-31" link1="Not a Proceedings" style1="bold" link2="AMS presentation" url2="http://ams.confex.com/ams/91Annual/webprogram/Paper184631.html">Not a Proceedings: AMS presentation.</practice>
				</examples>
			<otherPractices>
				<otherPractice header="Use For Examples">
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08" link1="Animation/moving image" style1="bold">Animation/moving image: use for clips, interviews, lectures, movies</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08" link1="Article" style1="bold">Article: use for reviews general articles, preprints, encyclopedia entries, comments, book forewords, comments on, replys, reply to comments; do not use for book review, use book review instead</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08" link1="Artifact/physical object" style1="bold">Artifact/physical object: use for physical specimens like ice cores, rock samples</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08" link1="Blog/forum/email list" style1="bold">Blog/forum/email list: use for message board, chat, weblog</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-05-31" link1="Book/monograph" style1="bold">Book/monograph: use for a citation for a whole book</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08" link1="Book review" style1="bold">Book review: use for book review only; use article for other reviews</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08" link1="Encyclopedia" style1="bold">Encyclopedia: use for when referring to the entire encyclopedia </practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08" link1="Image" style1="bold">Image: use for photos, maps, </practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08" link1="Interactive resource" style1="bold">Interactive resource: use for COMET modules, Web Weather for Kids</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08" link1="Manual" style1="bold">Manual: use for operations manuals, user guides</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08" link1="Manuscript" style1="bold">Manuscript: use for thesis, dissertation and SOARS papers</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08" link1="Report" style1="bold">Report: use for NCAR technical note</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08" link1="Software" style1="bold">Software: use for computer models like the WRF</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08" link1="Sound" style1="bold">Sound: use for voices, music, and natural world and  mechanical tones</practice>
					
				</otherPractice>
				<otherPractice header="Non-refereed Items">
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08">Books/monograph</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08">Book chapter</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08">Journals are often, but not always, peer-reviewed</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08">Magazine: except Science Magazine </practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08">Newsletter</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08">Poster</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08">Preprint</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08">Proceedings: some proceedings are peer-reviewed while others are not</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08">Report</practice>
					
				</otherPractice>
				<otherPractice header="Refereed Items (Generally)">
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08">Journals are often, but not always, peer-reviewed</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08">Science Magazine</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2010-06-08">Proceedings: some proceedings are peer-reviewed while others are not</practice>
				</otherPractice>
			</otherPractices>
		 </bestPractices>
		 <documentation>
				<obligation>required</obligation>
				<min>1</min>
				<max>1</max>
				<XMLdataTypes>
					<XMLdataType>string</XMLdataType>
				</XMLdataTypes>
				<domain>controlled vocabulary</domain>
				<example>Article</example>
			</documentation>
  </field>
<!--  removed from the schema 2011-05-02:			<termAndDeftn vocab="Proceedings">The published record of a conference, congress, symposium, or other meeting sponsored by a society or association.</termAndDeftn>-->

</metadataFieldInfo>
<!--LICENSE AND COPYRIGHT
The contents of this file are subject to the Educational Community License v1.0 (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License. You should obtain a copy of the License from http://www.opensource.org/licenses/ecl1.php. Files distributed under the License are distributed on an "AS IS" basis, WITHOUT WARRANTY OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the License for the specific language governing rights and limitations under the License. Copyright 2002-2009 by Digital Learning Sciences, University Corporation for Atmospheric Research (UCAR). All rights reserved.-->
