
<oai_dc:dc xmlns:oai_dc="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc/ http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/oai_dc.xsd">
  <dc:title>International Water Law Project</dc:title>
  <dc:subject>Policy issues</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>water law</dc:subject>
  <dc:subject>international water policy</dc:subject>
  <dc:date>2002-02-01</dc:date>
  <dc:description>This website provides information on international water law and policy. The International Water Law Project offers full text of many international and regional agreements, declarations and resolutions. Regional documents are organized by continent and then in many cases by waterway to reflect agreements for a particular river basin. The case law section provides examples from the Permanent Court of International Justice, the International Court of Justice and other tribunals. The site also includes current articles, news stories, and a publication bibliography as well as a table with water course information for the world's major rivers and links to agreements related to those waterways. Users may join a listserv that discusses international water law.</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Supports National Science Education Standards (NSES): 9-12:Content Standard F Science in Personal and Social Perspectives Standards:Natural resources</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Supports National Science Education Standards (NSES): 9-12:Content Standard F Science in Personal and Social Perspectives Standards:Environmental quality</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Supports National Council for Geographic Education (NCGE) standard: Human Systems:How forces of cooperation and conflict among people influence the division and control of Earth's surface</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Educational level is: General public</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Educational level is: Graduate or professional</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Educational level is: High school</dc:description>
  <dc:description>Educational level is: Undergraduate upper division</dc:description>
  <dc:contributor>Gabriel Eckstein</dc:contributor>
  <dc:contributor>Pacific Institute for Studies in Development, Environment and Security</dc:contributor>
  <dc:format>text/html</dc:format>
  <dc:type>Service:Listserv</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Text:Index or bibliography</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Text:Policy or procedure</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Text:Report</dc:type>
  <dc:type>Service</dc:type>
  <dc:identifier>http://www.internationalwaterlaw.org/</dc:identifier>
  <dc:language>en</dc:language>
  <dc:rights>Copyright, 2000, 2001, 2002 International Water Law Project. Permission is granted to use materials contained on this web site, in part or in full, for personal and educational purposes, but not commercial purposes, provided that you keep all copyright and other proprietary notices intact and provided that full credit is given to IWLP and the respective copyright, trademark, or other proprietary rights holder.</dc:rights>
</oai_dc:dc>
