<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: resourceType-adn-fields-en-us.xml,v 1.1 2009/01/30 21:34:12 ginger Exp $ -->
<metadataFieldInfo xmlns="http://www.dlese.org/Metadata/fields" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.dlese.org/Metadata/fields http://www.dlese.org/Metadata/fields/adn-item/0.6.50/resourceType.xsd">
	<field name="Resource type" id="re" language="en-us" metaFormat="adn" metaVersion="0.6.50" path="/itemRecord/educational/resourceTypes/resourceType">
		<definition>the nature, category, function or aggregation of resource content with an emphasis on how the resource may be used in the classroom, professional development or in an informal educational setting</definition>

		<vocabLevels number="3">
			<levelAndDeftn level="1" levelName="Responsible party" levelDeftn="the name of the group or organization responsible for the controlled vocabulary">
				<levelTermsAndDeftns>
					<levelTermAndDeftn term="DLESE">Digital Library for Earth System Education</levelTermAndDeftn>
				</levelTermsAndDeftns>
			</levelAndDeftn>				
			
			<levelAndDeftn level="2" levelName="Type" levelDeftn="the kind or format of the resource">
				<levelTermsAndDeftns>
					<levelTermAndDeftn term="Audio">resources whose content is primarily audio or intended to be realized in audio</levelTermAndDeftn>
					<levelTermAndDeftn term="Data">materials with primarily structured information encoded in lists, tables, databases etc., which will normally be in a format available for direct machine processing</levelTermAndDeftn>
					<levelTermAndDeftn term="Learning materials">materials prepared for use by students or teachers in the classroom, field or other learning environment. Some of the terms fit in a hierarchy with implied scope, specificity and length (e.g. from curriculum, to course, to module/unit, to lesson plan, to activity.</levelTermAndDeftn>
					<levelTermAndDeftn term="Offline">resources that exist only as physical objects and do not have URLs that describes how to order the resources</levelTermAndDeftn>
					<levelTermAndDeftn term="Portal">homepages that are the entrance to a large complex web sites holding a variety of related resources hosted by a single or group of related organizations. For example, www.nasa.gov is a portal. A portal also encompasses other resource types.</levelTermAndDeftn>
					<levelTermAndDeftn term="Service">systems that provides one or more functions of value to the end-user</levelTermAndDeftn>
					<levelTermAndDeftn term="Text">resources whose content contain primarily words for reading</levelTermAndDeftn>
					<levelTermAndDeftn term="Tool">resources that aids in accomplishing a task</levelTermAndDeftn>
					<levelTermAndDeftn term="Visual">resources with actual and symbolic visual representations other than text</levelTermAndDeftn>
				</levelTermsAndDeftns>
			</levelAndDeftn>				
			
			<levelAndDeftn level="3" levelName="Resource" levelDeftn="the name of the resource or object; see the allowed combination of terms below; the resource part of the term is the phrase after the last colon"/>
		</vocabLevels>

		<terms>
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Audio:Audio book" id="00">an audio recording of a book in print</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Audio:Audio webcast" id="01">the audio component (only) of a broadcast presented on or captured digitally from the web (e.g. podcast, newscast, speech, interviews)</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Audio:Lecture" id="02">an audio recording of a speech or classroom instruction</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Audio:Music" id="03">a recording of vocal, instrumental or mechanical sounds having rhythm, melody or harmony</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Audio:Oral history" id="04">recorded historical information obtained in interviews concerning personal experiences and recollections</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Audio:Radio broadcast" id="05">a recording of a newscast, talk show or other oral presentation originally generated via the radio</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Audio:Sound" id="06">recorded auditory material (e.g. natural world, mechanical, noise, tones)</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Data:In situ dataset" id="07">data measurements generated when the measuring instrument and the medium to be measured are in direct contact</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Data:Modeled dataset" id="08">data generated by equations, computer models and numerical simulations</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Data:Remotely sensed dataset" id="09">data measurements generated when the measuring instrument and the medium to be 	measured are not in direct contact</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Assessment" id="0a">materials that are designed to measure student learning (exams, questionnaires, quizzes) or to support teacher design or development of such materials (rubrics). Materials that support existing assessments (answer keys). Materials that relate to the philosophy of assessment (articles about performance and authentic assessment, for example).</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Case study" id="0b">an intensive analysis of an individual unit (as a person or community) stressing developmental factors in relation to environment or a scientific study of a specific location or region</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Classroom activity" id="0c">a classroom-based task or exercise, often part of a lesson plan or other larger unit of instruction, that helps student develop particular skills, knowledge, or habits of mind. Usually, activity goals and outcomes are specific.</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Computer activity" id="0d">a computer-based task or exercise, often part of a lesson plan or other larger unit of instruction, that helps students develop particular skills, knowledge, or habits of mind. Usually, activity goals and outcomes are specific (e.g. Mountain Simulation: Assignment).</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Course" id="0e">a sequence of instructional units done over a semester or quarter that are designed by teachers, faculty, or a group of instructors to significantly advance student skills, knowledge, and habits of mind in a particular discipline and to help students meet specified requirements as set forth in a curricula or district or state policy (e.g. Introduction to the Atmosphere)</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Curriculum" id="0f">a program of study. Examples include academic standards, (the knowledge, skills and habits of mind students are expected to acquire in particular grade levels or clusters of grade levels) and the units of instruction, often with sample lesson plans, illustrative student activities, and essential and supplementary resources that can help students reach standards. Curricula are often designed at the state or school district level, but can also apply to a program of study required for a particular university or college-issued degree.</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Field activity" id="0g">a field-based task or exercise, often part of a lesson plan or other larger unit of instruction, to help student develop particular or habits of mind. Usually, the goals and outcomes are specific.</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Field trip guide" id="0h">directions or suggestions for learning experiences outside of the classroom, usually off-site, either general or specific to a particular location</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Instructor guide" id="0i">supporting material for teachers regarding the use of learning materials with respect to learning objectives, classroom management, materials and assessment</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Lab activity" id="0j">a laboratory-based task or exercise, often part of a lesson plan or other larger unit of instruction, to help students develop particular skills, knowledge, or habits of mind; usually, the goals and outcomes are specific</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Lesson plan" id="0k">a plan for helping students learn a particular set of skills, knowledge or habits of mind; often includes student activities as well as teaching ideas, instructional materials, and other resources; is shorter in duration than and often a part of a unit or module</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Module or unit" id="0l">a sequence of lesson plans designed to teach a set of skills, knowledge and habits of mind (e.g. Understanding the Water Cycle)</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Presentation or demonstration" id="0m">a formal representation of ideas that is illustrated to others either visually or by the act of doing (e.g. PowerPoint slides)</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Problem set" id="0n">a series of tasks or questions posed to the student, as in a homework or other assignment</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Project" id="0o">activities organized around a particular academic topic where goals and outcomes are generally broad in nature and interactions with others often occur</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Syllabus" id="0p">general material describing a course or unit of study, includes outlines and table of 	contents</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Tutorial" id="0q">a resource that provides guided, practical information about a specific subject or task</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Learning materials:Virtual field trip" id="0r">a series of on-line visual and text-based resources that mimic a field trip experience in an electronic setting</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Offline:Physical object" id="0s">a reference to a non-web-based entity like a book, CD-ROM or rock sample which does not have an URL at which the object can be ordered</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Portal:Commercial portal" id="0t">generally a URL that includes .com or .biz as part of the website address</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Portal:Educational portal" id="0u">generally a URL that includes .edu as part of the website address</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Portal:Government portal" id="0v">generally a URL that includes .gov as part of the website address </termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Portal:Nonprofit portal" id="0w">generally a URL that includes .org or .museum as part of the website address</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Service:Ask an expert" id="0x">a site where one can submit questions for personal response to either an individual or group of 	people who have specific expertise in the area of interest</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Service:Clearinghouse" id="0y">a site that offers links to other sites organized around a topic or topics. The linked to sites are hosted by unrelated organizations. This is different than portal where the linked to sites are hosted by a single or related organizations.</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Service:Forum or discussion" id="0z">an interface where a group of individuals can engage in text-based talk about a particular subject; may or may not be synchronous (e.g. blogs)</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Service:Listserv" id="000">an email based communication that are usually topic-focused and distributed to a member-based group of individuals via a single email address</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Service:Message board" id="001">interface whereby individuals can post information, requests or ideas for view by others	</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Service:Search engine" id="002">mechanism by which the Internet or some sub-component is searched based on a specific query entered by the user (more extensive than Search this Site)</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Text:Abstract or summary" id="003">a condensed version of a larger piece of work, outlining the major points and conclusions</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Text:Book" id="005">a long written composition (includes literature, technical documentation and guides, excluding field and instructor guides)</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Text:Glossary" id="006">a collection of specialized terms and their meanings</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Text:Index or bibliography" id="007">a list (as of bibliographical information or citations to a body of literature) arranged usually in alphabetical order of some specified datum (as author, subject, or keyword); a list often with descriptive or critical notes of writings relating to a particular subject, period, or author; a list of works written by an author or printed by a publishing house; the works or a list of the works referred to in a text or consulted by the author in its production</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Text:Journal article" id="008">a writing that shares ideas or research results which appear in a periodical publication that is often peer-reviewed and of an academic nature</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Text:Periodical" id="009">a publication that is produced on some predictable schedule, such as weekly, monthly or annually</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Text:Policy or procedure" id="00a">a document containing statements or a series of steps to accomplish something</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Text:Proceedings" id="00b">a collection of papers or abstracts presented at a specific meeting or event</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Text:Proposal" id="00c">a formal document that outlines a specific project, recommendation, plan or idea</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Text:Reference" id="00d">a work containing useful facts or information (e.g. user's guides, technical manuals). A student might consult this during independent research. It does not have a guided component. It may comprise hyperlinked pages but a specific path through it is not designated.</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Text:Report" id="00e">a detailed account or statement outlining the results or events of a meeting, endeavor, activity or study (e.g. review, evaluation)</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Text:Thesis" id="00f">scholarly work for an academic degree</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:To be supplied" id="00g">a placeholder term when an appropriate resource type value has yet to be determined</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Tool:Calculation or conversion tool" id="00h">a tool for mathematical manipulations (e.g. Celsius to Fahrenheit,  satellite tracker)</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Tool:Code" id="00i">computer instructions that allows for the enhancement of a resource; it generally does not stand alone (e.g. numerical models, applets)</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Tool:Software" id="00j">a tool that allows access, interactions with or the ability to run resources; it does not enhance another piece of software rather it stands alone, (e.g. tools to look at and analyze data or create learning materials)</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Visual:Artistic illustration" id="00k">a visual not generated from data and not meant to illustrate a scientific concept or process (e.g. artistic drawing, animations, clip art, virtual tours)</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Visual:Map" id="00l">a 2-D representation of physical data at a single point in time or space that illustrate fairly static physical features (e.g. topographic, soil, road or bedrock maps, etc.). For weather or forecast maps, use scientific visualization.</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Visual:Photograph" id="00m">an image that has been taken with a camera and is available either online or offline</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Visual:Remotely sensed imagery" id="00n">imagery generated from measuring devices that are not in direct contact with the medium they are measuring (e.g. radar or satellite imagery)</termAndDeftn>

			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Visual:Scientific illustration" id="00o">still or animated images, not based directly on data, that illustrate scientific concepts or processes through diagrams, graphs, figures or virtual reality (e.g. The Wilson Cycle)</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Visual:Scientific visualization" id="00p">dynamic or static visuals generated from physical data or model output (e.g. simulations, animations, weather forecast maps or streamflow maps)</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Visual:Video" id="00q">animated images for use on a computer or television screen (e.g. clips, interviews, lectures, movies, etc.)</termAndDeftn>
	
			<termAndDeftn vocab="DLESE:Visual:Visual webcast" id="00r">a predominantly image related broadcast or podcast presented on or captured from the Internet (may include audio)</termAndDeftn>
		</terms>

		<bestPractices>
			<dos>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2002-10-22">Use audio for recorded items that have no visual component.</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2005-04-25" link1="Activity" style1="bold" link2="Lesson plan" style2="bold" link3="Module or unit" style3="bold" link4="Course" style4="bold">Some resource types comprise other resource types such that an Activity is part of a Lesson plan which is part of a Module or unit which is part of a Course which is part of a Curriculum. Indicate the largest resource type that applies.</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2005-04-25" link1="Virtual field trip" style1="bold" link2="Visual:Scientific visualization/illustration" style2="bold" link3="description - resource" style3="bold">If a Virtual field trip has an animation that illustrates a concept or process of more general interest, then include the resource type Visual:Scientific visualization/illustration and be sure the concept illustrated is described in the description - resource field.</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2006-07-28" link1="Virtual field trip" style1="bold" link2="Visual:Photograph" style2="bold">If a Virtual field trip has many photographs, the resource type of Visual:Photograph may be included.</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2005-04-25" link1="Service:Search engine" style1="bold">Use the term Service:Search engine when the resource provides a mechanism to search it internal holdings based on a specific query entered by a user (more extensive than Search this site).</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12" link1="Portal" style1="bold" link2="Service:Clearinghouse" style2="bold">When using the terms Portal and Service:Clearinghouse, note the distinction between the two definitions in the focus of the relationship of the source of the linked material to the host organization. Portals generally provide links to in-house materials while Clearinghouses link to materials form multiple sources.</practice>

<!-- Obsolete practices - do not erase - keep for historical purposes
				<practice status="current" originDate="2002-10-22">If the resource has a well-defined use outside its general intended context of use, select additional resource types that apply.</practice>
				<practice status="hide" originDate="2002-10-22" archDate="2005-04-25">Apply the idea that some resource types have relationships such that one can comprise another. For example: Curriculum -&gt; Course -&gt;Module/unit -&gt; Lesson plan -&gt; Activity is the hierarchy we envision</practice>

				<practice status="hide" originDate="2002-10-22">A virtual field trip is almost certainly going to contain photographs.. hence do not include a resource type of Visual:Photograph. However if the virtual field trip has an animation to enhance the "visit" that illustrates a concept or process of more general interest, then add a resource type of Visual:Scientific visualization/illustration and be sure the concept illustrated is described in the metadata field of description.</practice>

				<practice status="obsolete" originDate="2002-10-22" archDate="2005-04-25">Enter at least 1 resource type first by choosing a category then a name. As each resource type is entered, it appears in the table alphabetically. If you make a mistake you can delete the entry. </practice>
				<practice status="obsolete" originDate="2002-10-22" archDate="2005-04-25">For each different resource type, create an entry in the table.</practice>
				<practice status="hide" originDate="2002-10-22" archDate="2005-04-25">Apply the idea "does this item have a use outside of the current context of this resource?". If so you may choose to select additional resource types (see examples below).</practice>
				<practice status="hide" originDate="2002-10-22" archDate="2005-04-25">Use resource type Service:Search Engine when the site provides a mechanism to search the web at large. If the site has only a "search this site " link, do not use this resource type.</practice>
-->
			</dos>
			
			<donts>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2002-10-22" link1="Portal" style1="bold" link2="Learning Materials or Visual" style2="bold">For the choice of Portal (e.g. www.nasa.gov), generally do not enter other resource types like Learning Materials or Visual etc. because a portal by definition implies a diverse group of resources. Enter a second resource type if there is something especially unique about the resource or if adding another resource type describes the bulk of the material on the portal site (e.g. if the portal consists entirely of images, photographs or datasets).</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2002-10-22">Do not let URL extensions like .com, .org, etc. be a primary influence on your choice of resource type.</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2005-04-25" link1="Service:Search engine" style1="bold">Do not use the term Service:Search engine for search this site links. It is intended for when more advanced searching capabilities are provided.</practice>

<!--Obsolete practices - do not erase - keep for historical purposes
				<practice status="obsolete" originDate="2005-04-25" archDate="2006-07-28" link1="Virtual field trip" style1="bold" link2="Visual:Photograph" style2="bold">Since Virtual field trip tends to include photographs, do not include a resource type of Visual:Photograph.</practice>
				<practice status="hide" originDate="2002-10-22">A virtual field trip is almost certainly going to contain photographs.. hence do not include a resource type of Visual:Photograph. However if the virtual field trip has an animation to enhance the "visit" that illustrates a concept or process of more general interest, then add a resource type of Visual:Scientific visualization/illustration and be sure the concept illustrated is described in the metadata field of description.</practice>
				<practice status="hide" originDate="2002-10-22" archDate="2005-04-25">Use resource type Service:Search Engine when the site provides a mechanism to search the web at large. If the site has only a "search this site " link, do not use this resource type.</practice>
				<practice status="obsolete" originDate="2002-10-22" archDate="2005-04-25">Do not exceed 8 different resource types.</practice>
				<practice status="obsolete" originDate="2002-10-22" archDate="2005-04-25">Do not enter the same resource types twice. The cataloger will not create a duplicate entry.</practice>
-->
			</donts>
			
			<examples>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2005-04-25" link1=" Learning Materials:Course" style1="bold">If a resource is a course, assume it includes the common elements of a course like a syllabus; select Learning Materials:Course as the resource type.</practice>

				<practice status="current" originDate="2002-10-22" link1="Learning Materials:Syllabus" style1="bold">If only a syllabus is available, select Learning Materials:Syllabus as the resource type.</practice>

				<practice status="current" originDate="2002-10-22" link1="Learning Materials:Tutorial" style1="bold" link2="The Hydrologic Cycle" url2="http://ww2010.atmos.uiuc.edu/(Gh)/guides/mtr/hyd/home.rxml">Learning Materials:Tutorial: The Hydrologic Cycle.</practice>

				<practice status="current" originDate="2002-10-22" link1="Text:Reference" style1="bold" link2="Crystallography" url2="http://webmineral.com/crystall.shtml">Text:Reference: Crystallography.</practice>

				<practice status="current" originDate="2002-10-22" link1="Text:Report" style1="bold" link2="Lava covers Kalapana, April - January 1991" url2="http://hvo.wr.usgs.gov/kilauea/history/1990Kalapana/" link3="Ice Core Contributions To Global Change Research: Past Successes and Future Directions" url3="http://www.nicl-smo.sr.unh.edu/documents/1998/index.html">Text:Report: Lava covers Kalapana, April - January 1991 and Ice Core Contributions To Global Change Research: Past Successes and Future Directions.</practice>

				<practice status="current" originDate="2002-10-22" link1="Learning Materials:Classroom activity, Text:Report, Text:Reference and Learning Materials:Instructor guide" style1="bold" link2="The Kids and Teachers Corner of the Year of the Ocean" url2="http://www.yoto98.noaa.gov/kids.htm">An example of a combination of resource types (Learning Materials:Classroom activity, Text:Report, Text:Reference and Learning Materials:Instructor guide ) is The Kids and Teachers Corner of the Year of the Ocean.</practice>

				<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12" link1="Visual:Scientific visualization" style1="bold" link2="Idealized ENSO Simulation" url2="http://www.cdc.noaa.gov/people/joseph.barsugli/anim.html">Visual:Scientific visualization: Idealized ENSO Simulation</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12" link1="Learning materials:Classroom activity" style1="bold" link2="Leaf Classification" url2="http://www.globe.gov/tctg/land_la_leafclass.pdf?sectionId=220">Learning materials:Classroom activity: Leaf Classification</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12" link1="Learning materials:Lesson plan" style1="bold" link2="Earthquake Patterns" url2="http://teachingboxes.org/earthquakes/lessons/lesson3.jsp">Learning materials:Lesson plan: Earthquake Patterns</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12" link1="Learning materials: Module or unit" style1="bold" link2="Living in Earthquake Country" url2="http://teachingboxes.org/earthquakes/index.jsp">Learning materials: Module or unit: Living in Earthquake Country</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12" link1="Visual:Scientific illustration" style1="bold" link2="The Rock Cycle" url2="http://wrgis.wr.usgs.gov/docs/parks/rxmin/rockcycle.pdf">Visual:Scientific illustration: The Rock Cycle</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2006-07-28" link1="Service:Clearinghouse" style1="bold" link2="Resources for Earth Sciences and Geography Education" url2="http://webs.cmich.edu/resgi/">Service:Clearinghouse: Resources for Earth Sciences and Geography Education</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2006-07-28" link1="Portal:Government portal" style1="bold" link2="National Climatic Data Center" url2="http://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/oa/ncdc.html">Portal:Government portal: National Climatic Data Center</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2006-07-28" link1="Portal:Educational portal" style1="bold" link2="University of California, Berkeley: Museum of Paleontology" url2="http://www.ucmp.berkeley.edu/">Portal:Educational portal: University of California, Berkeley: Museum of Paleontology</practice>
				<practice status="current" originDate="2006-07-28" link1="Portal:Government portal" style1="bold" link2="Visual:Photograph" style2="bold" link3="The Gateway to Astronaut Photography" url3="http://eol.jsc.nasa.gov/Education/">Portal:Government portal and Visual:Photograph: The Gateway to Astronaut Photography</practice>

<!--Obsolete practices - do not delete - keep for historical purposes
				<practice status="hide" originDate="2002-10-22" archDate="2005-04-25">If a resource is an entire course on-line, it is assumed to include the common elements of a course, such as a syllabus. So select a resource type of Learning Materials:Course .</practice>
				<practice status="hide" originDate="2002-10-22" archDate="2005-04-25">If the only thing available on-line is the syllabus, then use resource types of Learning Materials:Course and Learning Materials:Syllabus.</practice>
				<practice status="hide" originDate="2002-10-22">A virtual field trip is almost certainly going to contain photographs.. hence do not include a resource type of Visual:Photograph. However if the virtual field trip has an animation to enhance the "visit" that illustrates a concept or process of more general interest, then add a resource type of Visual:Scientific visualization/illustration and be sure the concept illustrated is described in the metadata field of description.</practice>
-->
			</examples>
			<otherPractices>
				<otherPractice header="More definition information">
					<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12">The following overarching categories used in this vocabulary have the following meanings.</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12" link1="Audio" style1="bold">Audio: resources whose content is primarily audio or intended to be realized in audio.</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12" link1="Data" style1="bold">Data: materials with primarily structured information encoded in lists, tables, databases etc., which will normally be in a format available for direct machine processing</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12" link1="Learning materials" style1="bold">Learning materials: materials prepared for use by students or teachers in the classroom, field or other learning environment. Some of the terms fit in a hierarchy with implied scope, specificity and length (e.g. from curriculum, to course, to module/unit, to lesson plan, to activity</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12" link1="Offline" style1="bold">Offline: resources that exist only as physical objects and do not have URLs that describes how to order the resources</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12" link1="Portal" style1="bold">Portal: homepages that are the entrance to a large complex web sites holding a variety of related resources hosted by a single or group of related organizations. For example, www.nasa.gov is a portal. A portal also encompasses other resource types.</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12" link1="Service" style1="bold">Service: systems that provides one or more functions of value to the end-user</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12" link1="Text" style1="bold">Text: resources whose content contain primarily words for reading</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12" link1="Tool" style1="bold">Tool: resources that aids in accomplishing a task</practice>
					<practice status="current" originDate="2006-06-12" link1="Visual" style1="bold">Visual: resources with actual and symbolic visual representations other than text</practice>
					

				</otherPractice>
			</otherPractices>
		</bestPractices>

		<documentation>
			<obligation>required</obligation>
			<min>1</min>
			<max>unbounded</max>
			<XMLdataTypes>
				<XMLdataType>string</XMLdataType>
			</XMLdataTypes>
			<domain>controlled vocabulary</domain>
			<example>DLESE:Visual:Map, DLESE:Text:Reference</example>
		</documentation>
	</field>
</metadataFieldInfo>
<!--	*** LICENSE INFORMATION *****
		Copyright 2002, 2003, 2004, 2005 DLESE Program Center
		University Corporation for Atmospheric Research (UCAR)
		P.O. Box 3000, Boulder, CO 80307, United States of America
		email: support@dlese.org. 
These XML instance documents are free software; you can redistribute them and/or modify them under the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later version.  These XML instance documents are distributed in the hope that they will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General Public License for more details. You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License along with this project; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307 USA -->
